Today's דף daf is ס"א Samech Aleph 61. We pick up at
the top, the issue we're in the middle of the section, the
final section of the sixth פרק, perek, which focuses on the חיוב
chiyuv of אש, eish, the liability for fire, and we're in the
middle of a fascinating אגדתא Agadata where based on these verses in
שמואל Shmuel and in דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim
where דוד המלך David HaMelech is asking for, is,
it's read, this strange story where he sent to get water. He
said, "Who would give me water to drink?" and some of his
soldiers broke through to the camp of the פלשתים Plishtim to retrieve
the water, and it said then he refused to drink it and
he poured it as a libation. And so that was very strange,
what was going on there? And in one version of the story,
there was a field filled, the פלשתים Plishtim were hiding in the
field and the field was filled with lentils, and in another version
of the story, the field was filled with barley. So what does
all of this mean? So the גמרא Gemara basically translates it that
the water really represented the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and he was looking for
a פסק, psak, and three versions of what type of a פסק
psak he was looking for. One was what was the הלכה halacha
about something that was buried, hidden in a fire? So that's why
we're bringing it up here. And the two other versions is he
wanted to know are you allowed to burn down these piles of
grain if the פלשתים Plishtim are hiding there to save yourself, but
it is you're saving yourself with your friend's property, בא להציל עצמו
בממון של חברו. ba lehatzil atzmo b'mamon shel chavero. And the third
version was they wanted to know if he could take one of
the piles to feed his animals in order to repay them with
the other piles. So according to the last two versions, they basically
told him technically you're not allowed to do that, you're not allowed
to burn down, save yourself with your friend's property, you're not allowed
to steal something with the intention to replace, but you're a king
and you are allowed to do that
because a king can do what he wants in terms of people's
property and so on. So those are the different sort of versions
of the אגדתא. Agadata. We're going to wrap that up right now.
The
גמרא, Gemara, I should just say that the issue, two issues very
important, practical issues that we raised yesterday, that came up yesterday, is
the idea that you're not allowed to save yourself with your friend's
property is a very strange idea.
In Judaism, the general principle is that you can do anything to
save a life with the exception of the three major things. Nobody
ever said you can
violate any sin to save a life except for עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, גילוי עריות, Gilui Arayot, שפיכות דמים, Shefichat Damim, and stealing, right?
So it's very strange and that leads תוספות Tosafot to say that
we're talking and a lot of ראשונים Rishonim to say that obviously
you're allowed
to steal or whatever or damage somebody's property in the process of
saving a life, but you just have to pay back, and the
question is are you allowed to do it without having to pay
back. You can sort of maybe try to frame it otherwise as
about like it was a very distant concern, it wasn't an immediate
concern that his life was really in danger. The issue that I
wanted to raise yesterday was normally when we speak about you can
do an עבירה, avera, the עבירה avera it's just a question about
the sin element of it, but here the question is about you're
actually injuring somebody else, and maybe you can't do anything you want
to protect life if somebody else's injury. Now of course we say
you can't murder, so it sounds like anything that's short of murder
you'd be allowed, but it's not so clear, like would you be
able to blind somebody for the sake of saving your life? What
stage could you actually inflict injury on another person to protect your
own life? But it still does seem even if you put limits
on that, it still does seem that property which is completely
replaceable should be an obvious that you're allowed to do it, so
it is strange the simple sense of this גמרא Gemara that says
you're not allowed to, which is why תוספות Tosafot rereads it. The
other point though I wanted to make which we skipped over yesterday,
which is important, is a really I think bigger question of whether
normal rules apply during wartime,
especially rules that relate to property and person, because what's a war?
A war is when you're going and you're destroying property and person.
So the idea that here he is in the context of fighting
against the פלשתים Plishtim and the question is will he have to
compensate this person for the property and so on. I don't know,
if you're in the middle of a war and you're driving your
tanks through somebody's field, you don't have to go ahead afterwards and
compensate the person, even if they're on your
side, even if they're one of your countrymen. So it's a strange
type of a question. Now maybe he sees that it's less about
a major war and more about like a small conflict. Thank you
so much. But it is strange that the גמרא Gemara sort of
assumes, treats this as a question of like a personal saving of
your life and a personal question of like if
an army goes through a place, they confiscate the property to feed
their troops and their horses, back when we had horses.
So the question, oh can I take it, do I take it
with the intention to pay back. It's funny that it reads this
at a very personal level and not in a context of war.
Maybe again it just assumes that just because he was fighting the
פלשתים Plishtim doesn't mean all of a sudden it becomes a larger
context of war, could have been like a local skirmish or something,
but it is very interesting from that perspective. So let's now continue
in the גמרא, Gemara, yeah.
I think we had a discussion earlier about using appropriate force, so
how does this fit in like if you're being attacked by somebody
personally? Can you—do you have to be concerned how much force you
use to protect yourself?
Yeah, so that's a good question. We normally—normally you say, yeah,
so there's a whole question about יכול להציל באחד מאיבריו, Yakhol Lehatzil
Be'echad Me'eivarav, like if you're intervening to save somebody who's being like
pursued and you could save the person with a lesser use of
force, so you're not—you're liable if you use a greater amount of
force. But the question is, like, what does it mean you
could? If you find yourself sort of like in that situation,
who—and you have to use the full amount of force necessary so
that you can be certain that you will, right. So I mean,
so yes, I mean, I assume that we define
very generously the parameters of what means, like, you needed to. But
if it's a clear case where you didn't need to, then it
would be different. Some אחרונים Akhronim want to make a distinction also
between the sort of standards we apply to the person who himself
or herself is being pursued and a third party, that the person
being pursued has more latitude than a third party. But those are
good questions.
Like what's happening now, like the Hebron soldier, or the police in
London.
Right, exactly. Yeah, yeah, those are really critical questions. How do you—how
do you define necessary force, especially when you're in a stressful situation
and you know you need to? So those are the questions, yeah,
absolutely. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says now, picking up at the
top of
ס''א ע''א. Samekh Alef Amud Alef. Okay, בשלמא למאן דאמר הני תרתי,
Bishlama Leman De'amar Hani Tartei, according to those that say the explanation
either that he got a ruling about whether he could save himself
with somebody else's property, whether he would have to pay back, let's
say reading תוספות Tosafot way, or whether he could take the barley
to pay back the lentils. So he got a ruling that technically
he's not—that a normal person isn't allowed, but he is because he's
a king. So then it—and then it says that he—so he chose
to do—not use his king prerogative. That's what we read yesterday. So
it works according to those. היינו דכתיב, Hainu De-chtiv, what the verse
says, ולא אבה דוד לשתותם. Ve-lo Ava David Lishtotam. דוד David didn't
want to drink them, meaning he didn't want to accept the פסק
Psak that allowed him to do it because just by virtue of
him being a king he wanted to—he didn't want to take the
king's prerogative. אמר כיון דאיכא איסורא, Amar Keivan De'ika Issura, since it's
basically forbidden, לא ניחא לי, Lo Nikha Li, I don't want to
do it even though I have—I'm allowed to as a king. אלא
למאן דאמר טמון דאש קמיבעיא ליה, Ela Leman De'amar Tamun De-Esh Kamibaya
Lei, but if his whole question was, what's the הלכה Halacha if
I burned down the stacks and there's something buried in there, if
I have to pay for it? מאי ולא אבה דוד לשתותם, Mai
Ve-lo Ava David Lishtotam, what does it mean he didn't want to
drink them? If it's just a פסק Psak question, does he have
to reimburse for the stuff that was hidden or not? So the
גמרא Gemara says, זו אמרוה משמיה. Zu Amrinuhu Mishmaya Hi. He didn't
say it over in the name of—apparently he sent
his—or he didn't send them, but these valorous soldiers went to, it
says, to break through the camp of the פלשתים Plishtim to get
the water. So in this version, the water is the teaching of
the תורה. Torah.
So they somehow had to break through the פלשתים Plishtim in order
to go to the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and get the פסק Psak and
bring the פסק Psak back to דוד. David. So דוד David did
not want to tell over the פסק Psak in the name of
these valorous men who went ahead and retrieved it. Why? You would
think they deserve all the more honor, but אמר כך מקובלני מבית
דינו של שמואל הרמתי: Amar Kach Mekubalni Mi-Beis Dino Shel Shmuel HaRamati:
this is the tradition I have from the בית דין Beis Din
of שמואל הרמתי—not Shmuel HaRamati to be confused with the אמורא שמואל,
Amora Shmuel,
since we're making דוד David into a rabbi in this story—כל המוסר
עצמו למות על דברי תורה, Kol HaMoser Atzmo Lamut Al Divrei Torah,
anybody who is willing—who goes ahead and, like, risks their life for
the sake of תורה, Torah, אין אומרים דבר הלכה משמו: Ein Omrin
Devar Halacha Mishmo: you don't say הלכה Halacha in his name. Now
that's strange, you would think he deserves all the more honor. But
actually, the way the מהרש''א Maharsha reads this, reads this as a
critique. Like you might say, זאת התורה אדם כי ימות באוהל, Zot
HaTorah Adam Ki Yamut BaOhel, אין התורה נקנית אלא במי שממית עצמו
עליה, Ein HaTorah Niknat Ela Be-mi Shememit Atzmo Aleha,
it's the same phrase. תורה Torah is acquired by somebody who's willing
to, like, sacrifice their life for it, but that's a metaphor. That's
not literal. Okay, so you're not really supposed to risk your life
just to get some פסק הלכה. Psak Halacha. Okay, so and the
מהרש''א Maharsha says that like, if the whole idea that you say
over תורה Torah in the name of the person who teaches it
is because it מביא גאולה לעולם, Maivi Geula La'olam, brings redemption to
the world, so
somebody who is basically prepared to risk life for an unnecessary
purpose—תורה Torah is not one of the things you literally risk your
life for—so then, they're not worthy of that merit. So it's quite
fascinating that you read the story. I mean it also explains why
normally we read דוד David didn't want to drink it, that actually
is closer to the whatever the Whatever the פשט pshat is going
on there in those פסוקים, psukim, it seems like David was sort
of just like wistfully saying, "Oh, I wish I had some water,"
and then they actually risked their lives and David actually felt like
that was a stupid thing to do. I'm not going to drink
the water that you went ahead and, you know, for no purpose
like risked your lives, maybe risked other people's lives and so on.
So that's sort of what the גמרא Gemara is now saying, but
learning it as talking about תורה. Torah. Okay. Now, ויסך אתם להשם,
Vayisech osam l'Hashem, and he poured the water out as some ointment
to God. בשלמא למאן דאמר הני תרתי, Bishlama l'man d'amar hanai tartei,
if it's one of these two things about the issue about the
taking in order to pay back or saving yourself or somebody else's
property, משום דעביד לשם שמים, mishum d'avid l'shem shamayim,
because it means that he acted in sort of sake of heaven.
He could have done these acts because he was the king, but
because he was being righteous he didn't, because a normal commoner would
not have been allowed to do it. אלא למאן דאמר תלמוד דאש,
Ela l'man d'amar talmud d'esh, but according to the one that says
it was just a פסק psak about whether you had to reimburse
for something that was hidden in the, you know, when the fire
burnt it down, מאי ויסך אתם להשם, Mai Vayisech osam l'Hashem, what
did it mean he anointed it to God? דאמרינה משמא דגמרא, Damrina
mishma d'gemara,
it means rather than attributing it to these, you know, these soldiers
who broke through, he gave it to God. He said it in
the name of the anonymous tradition. So this teaching, this water as
it were, is now God's water, wasn't their water, right? So it
was somehow part of the anonymous tradition. Okay, that was a fascinating
end to that story, and interesting with all the discussion of fire,
have a little discussion about water, you know, and water as תורה.
Torah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, or the next משנה.
Mishnah. Back to technical issues about fire. עבר גדר שהוא גבוה ארבע
אמות, Avar geder sheguvo'ah arba amot, if the fire passed over a
גדר—now geder we normally translate a גדר geder as a fence, but
גדר geder normally means like a wall of bricks, a wall of
stone—which is ארבע אמות arba amot high, או דרך הרבים, o derech
harabim, or passed through a path of the, you know, like a
common thoroughfare, which is basically understood to be שש עשרה אמה, shesh
esreh amah, like twenty-four feet wide, או נהר, o nahar, or passed
through a river, פטור, patur, you're exempt. This is a question about
what constitutes a legitimate שמירה shmira of the fire, right? So if
the fire can't spread with a רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, that's fine,
then it's not—then you're not—fundamentally haven't created the hazard. Let's say it
could spread, but you've got a big wall around your property. Okay,
so here it says, okay, if the wall is ארבע אמות arba
amot high. Now really ארבע אמות arba amot is six feet. So
again, I don't know, I mean I assume a normal fire if
it spread in your property six feet will contain it, right? But
sometimes it gets out of control.
But it's at the region edge of your property,
it's a pretty big fire. That's true too, right? Right, and we're
going to see in a minute also where is it in your
property, you know, how much of your just property is around it
before it gets to the edge of your property. Right, so it's
hard to—so and, you know, you'd all think it's all according to
the size of the fire, right? Or all according to what you—how
you could imagine how potentially the fire could grow. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does with it.
ותניא, V'tanya, but didn't we teach in a ברייתא: braitza: עבר גדר
שהוא גבוה ארבע אמות חייב. Avar geder sheguvo'ah arba amot chayav. That
if it's ארבע אמות arba amot high you're חייב. chayav. And it
doesn't say how high, maybe it's sort of basically trying to say
that no matter how high the wall is, or it's not clear
in that ברייתא braitza when you would be exempt. So אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, תנא דידן כחשיב מלמעלה למטה. tanna didan k'chashi
mil'ma'ala l'mata. So we're going to try to reconcile the two. תנא
דידן כחשיב מלמעלה למטה. Tanna didan k'chashi mil'ma'ala l'mata. Our תנא Tanna
is going from a big wall down. שש אמות פטור, Shesh amot
patur, חמש אמות פטור, chamesh amot patur, six you're פטור, patur, five
you're פטור, patur, עד ארבע אמות פטור. ad arba amot patur. You're
פטור patur until you get to ארבע אמות. arba amot. So when
it says you're פטור patur ארבע אמות, arba amot, it means up
to ארבע אמות arba amot you're פטור, patur, less you're חייב. chayav.
Okay, that was pretty clear. תנא ברא, Tanna bara, the other, the
outer תנא, Tanna, the—the ברייתא, braitza, מלמטה למעלה כחשיב. mil'mata l'ma'ala k'chashi.
It's going from bottom up. שתי אמות חייב, Shtei amot chayav, two
אמות amot you're חייב, chayav, שלש אמות חייב, shalosh amot chayav, three
you're חייב, chayav, עד ארבע אמות חייב. ad arba amot chayav. You're
חייב chayav until four. So when it says you're חייב chayav ארבע
אמות חייב, arba amot chayav, it doesn't mean that, you know, that
like, you know, you're indefinitely חייב. chayav. It means up to ארבע
אמות arba amot you're חייב, chayav, anything more than ארבע אמות arba
amot you're פטור. patur. And when our משנה Mishnah says ארבע אמות
arba amot you're פטור, patur, it says once it's ארבע אמות arba
amot you're פטור. patur. So everybody sort of agrees that more than
ארבע אמות arba amot you're פטור. patur. The question is always what
about exactly ארבע אמות, arba amot, which one do you read which
way, but it's funny, you know. So one of them's read sort
of like up to ארבע אמות arba amot you're חייב, chayav, more
than that you're פטור. patur. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ארבע אמות שאמרו דפטור, arba amot she'amru d'patur,
אפילו בבית קוצים. afilu b'veit kotzim. Even—now we start get into the
specifics, because it should all depend on the circumstances. So he says
even if your field is filled with these thorns and thistles, which
is the case in the תורה, Torah, right? או מצא קוצים, o
matza kotzim, which presumably is like excellent kindling, right? It's thin, it's
small, it's dried out. So even if it's like likely apparently for
it to spread,
nevertheless you're exempt, which seems quite strange. Let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this, right? It shouldn't matter what the circumstances is.
So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. Where are we?
אפילו בבית קוצים. Afilu b'veit kotzim. אמר רב פפא... Amar Rav Pappa...
Where are we? אפילו בשדה קוצים. Afilu b'sade kotzim. אמר פפא Amar
Papa ומשפת קוצים ולמעלה ארבע אמות. u'misfas kotzim u'l'ma'ala arba amos. But
he says, ah, one minute though, it has to be from the
edge of the קוצים kotzim above ארבע אמות. arba amos. So if
you've got, let's say, a lot of wood laying on your ground,
okay, then the ארבע אמות arba amos is measured not from the
earth, but from the top of the fuel like the stuff that
the fire could be burning, okay, so where the base of the
fire would be or whatever, you know, it's so so if you've
there's a lot of thorns and thistles, it's ארבע אמות arba amos
higher than the top of the thorns. If there's a lot of,
you know, just wood and whatever and sticks, it's ארבע אמות arba
amos higher than the sticks. Okay, you would really want to say
maybe it could be ארבע אמות arba amos higher than the flame,
but then you don't know where that flame is going to be,
right? You start with your fire twenty feet away from the wall,
so as long you know, so you don't know how high the
flame is going to be when it gets to the wall. So
but as long as apparently as long as your wall is four
higher than whatever the sort of apparently, you know, fuel wood source,
fuel source is on the ground, that's considered to be high enough.
All right, so now let's see,
one minute, I just want to check תוספות, Tosafot, he has an
interesting explanation, one minute.
Yeah, okay, so it says like
this,
if you look at the last תוספות Tosafot עברה, Avra, at the
bottom of that תוספות Tosafot עברה, Avra, it says פשיטא peshita like
the last four lines of that תוספות Tosafot עברה, Avra, דמתניתין אעצי
דליקה קאי. dematnisin atzei deleika ka'ei. When the משנה Mishna says ארבע
אמות, arba amos, it means ארבע אמות arba amos higher than the
wood that you're using for the fire. I guess that means that
even if you're having, you know, if here's your field, if here's
your field and here's your wall, right, and you're having your fire
in the middle, right? So let's say, you know, let's say you've
got, you know, this is your, you know, like let's say this
is, you know, that's your woodpile, right, and here's your fire. So
תוספות Tosafot says it's clear from the משנה Mishna that you start
the ארבע אמות, arba amos, it has to be ארבע אמות arba
amos from the height of the woodpile. Okay, so right, so there's
two things: there's how high is the flame where you're actually making
it, and what's the fuel that's on the ground, right? So תוספות
Tosafot says it has to be ארבע אמות arba amos higher than
the sort of wood that's on the ground and ארבע אמות arba
amos also higher than the top of the woodpile, or you know,
where the, you know, where the fire is burning. I wonder if
you had a barbecue though. I'm serious. If you had a grill,
right, you know, you had like this grill and the fire was
here, so that have to be right? It have to be ארבע
אמות arba amos higher than that or is the fact that it's
like contained in the... presumably not. Presumably the only concern would be
if the grill knocked down, you know, and it spreads. So then
it would still be like ארבע אמות arba amos from the base
of the ground. Okay, so anyway, it's ארבע אמות arba amos from
where like the from the base of the fire, the top of
the wood source, of where the fire is burning or the wood
that's on the ground.
Okay, אפילו בשדה קוצים. Afilu b'sade kotzim. אמר פפא Amar Papa ומשפת
קוצים ולמעלה ארבע אמות. u'misfas kotzim u'l'ma'ala arba amos. אמר רב Amar
Rav לא שנו אלא בקולחת. lo shanu ela b'kolachas. All of this
is when the fire is like going up straight.
אבל במנשבת, Aval b'menasheves, if the fire is like, you know, like
leaning, right, bending, right, you know how those when the fire spread,
right, they're like at this angle, they're slanted. In that type of
a case, אפילו עד מאה אמה חייב. afilu ad me'ah ama chayav.
Now, there's a question what this means. רש״י Rashi says it means
even if it, you know, even if it goes across a hundred
אמות, amos, it's still חייב chayav because it'll just spread real widely
when it's at that angle. תוספות Tosafot says no, we're not talking
about the distance, we're talking about height, we're talking about a wall.
So תוספות Tosafot says it means even if a wall is a
hundred אמות amos high, apparently if a fire is like, you know,
once a fire is sort of blowing and moving in that type
of a way, then presumably it can go over even a very
high wall. Of course, I don't know, because you know, it presumably
it only becomes קולחת kolachas after it escapes, right? Presumably when you're
or מנשבת menasheves I mean. You know, when you're burning it, I
mean I don't know, maybe it means here I'm having a fire
and I'm still tending the fire and now it's starting, the wind
is moving it.
Or when you're clearly brushing.
Oh, that's interesting.
You're intentionally setting a fire to spread.
Oh, I never thought about that, but right, I always think about
a fire like I don't know, you're just trying to cook something
or for warmth. But you're right, you might actually be trying to
spread a fire to clear brush or something.
Otherwise it wouldn't make sense, because the fire could turn into...
Exactly, how do you know what it's going to turn into? It
sounds like while you're still tending to it, it's in that state.
So if you're tending to it, and it
starts, wait, even a double wall real quick?
Right, but but you have to know that if you're about to
do a fire that's מנשבת, menasheves, then you there's you're not going
to be exempt no matter how high.
Right, if you're going to do any fire that has the possibility
of...
Right, so that becomes that question. Right. Exactly. Yeah, I don't know,
that becomes exactly the question. So the fact your fire has the
potential to be מנשבת, menasheves, when do you measure מנשבת menasheves or
קולחת, kolachas, right? That's exactly the question.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says ושמואל אמר. u'Shmuel amar. No, our משנה Mishnah is that it's
at like it's bending, it's at an angle. אבל בקולחת, aval bekolachat,
but if it's a straight up fire, אפילו כל שהוא פטור, afilu
kol shehu patur, even a small wall you're פטור patur because again,
then—but that's always the question: how do you know that that קולחת
kolachat won't become a נכפסת? nichfeset? But anyway, presumably if it's going
straight up, we're not so afraid it's going to spread. תני כוותיה
דרב, tani kivatei de-rav, we taught like Rav, במה דברים אמורים בקולחת,
bameh devarim amurim be-kolachat, when it's straight up, אבל בנכפסת, aval be-nichfeset,
but if it's bending, העצים מצויים לה, ha-etzim metzuyim lo, and there's
available fuel, אפילו עד מאה מיל חייב. afilu ad me'ah mil chayav.
Even a hundred מיל mil you're חייב. chayav. Now, a מיל mil
is like a kilometer, so even if מאה אמות me'ah amot is
an exaggeration for a height of a wall, who makes a wall
a hundred אמות? amot? מאה מיל me'ah mil like Tosafot says, obviously
we're talking about distance. Nobody talks about height by saying מאה מיל.
me'ah mil. But Tosafot still wants to say we're talking about a
wall, so Tosafot says we're talking about the thickness of the wall,
which still is obviously an exaggeration, no wall's a hundred kilometers thick.
But anyway, but it's—it might be that this is talking about the
distance that it traverses and not about the height of the wall.
עבר נהר, avar nahar, and that because at the end of it
now it does talk about the distance that it's traversing. עבר נהר
או שלולית שהם רחבים שמונה אמות, avar nahar o shelulit she-hem rechavim
shmoneh amot, if it passes a river or a stream of water,
we'll see what a שלולית shelulit is in a minute, that's eight
אמות amot wide, פטור patur you're exempt. So that does sound like
we're talking. And then it's interesting, so even if you've got this
bending fire, if it traverses like a lot of straight ground, you'll
be חייב chayav because that's, you know, you have these forest fires,
right? They can traverse an enormous amount of area. But in terms
of a place of water, even with this type of a fire
presumably it won't traverse a place of water. Again, I don't know
if that's actually true. I mean, I imagine it needs fuel, you
know, but I don't know how these—I don't know the physics of
these fires. Okay. But again, the big question with all of this
is at what stage do we begin to measure this? Like at
what stage, when it's in your control, the potential, what's already happening
in your control? Like that's the key question. All right. דרך הרבים,
derech ha-rabim, now if it passes a public thoroughfare you're פטור. patur.
מאן
תנא, man tanna, who is the author of this? It says this.
אמר רבה רבי אלעזר היא, amar rabba rabbi elazar hi, it's Rabbi
Elazar. דתנן רבי אליעזר אומר שש עשרה אמות כדרך רשות הרבים, detnan
rabbi eliezer omer shesh esrei amot ke-derech reshut ha-rabim,
that the sixteen אמות amot is the width of a רשות הרבים.
reshut ha-rabim. Now why that shows that that's Rabbi Eliezer and what,
you know, his ruling about the normal width of רשות הרבים reshut
ha-rabim is is not exactly clear. But okay, anyway, but if it's
a very wide, if it's sixteen אמות amot wide, then it's—then that's
wide enough for you to be exempt. Now that's going to be
funny because we're going to see in a minute in the next
משנה mishnah that—that, you
know, sixteen אמות amot just of a straight
unimpeded distance might not, you know, if it's in your territory, might
not be enough to exempt you. So we'll get back to that
in a minute. או נהר, o nahar, or it passes through a
river. רב אמר נהר ממש, rav amar nahar mamash, literally a river.
ושמואל אמר אריסא
דדילוי, ushmuel amar arisa de-diluy, no, even something like an irrigation canal.
מאן דאמר נהר ממש, man de-amar nahar mamash, the one that says
a river exempts you, אף על גב דליכא מיא, af al gav
de-leika maya, even if there's no water, presumably it's wide enough or
because there's like the moisture there, you know? ומאן דאמר אריסא דדילוי,
u-man de-amar arisa de-diluy, and the one that says an irrigation canal,
אי אית ביה מיא אין, ei it beh maya in, only if
there's actually water in that canal, אבל אי לית ביה מיא לא,
aval i leit beh maya lo, but not if there's no water,
no, because then what's the big deal for it to cross—for it
to cross that canal? תנן התם, tnan hatam, now we taught over
there in פאה. peah. ואלו מפסיקין לפאה, ve-eilu mafsikin le-peah, the following
things divide a field into two fields that each field you have
to give פאה peah for, right? You have one big field, there's
a river running through it, is it one field or two fields?
You have to give פאה peah from each half or one פאה
peah for the whole thing. So הנחל, ha-nachal, a
wadi, והשלולית, ve-ha-shelulit, and this שלולית shelulit which we mentioned before, we'll
see in a minute what that is, ודרך היחיד ודרך הרבים, ve-derech
ha-yachid ve-derech ha-rabim, or just a simple path even an individual path
and certainly a path for the, you know, for a public thoroughfare.
מאי שלולית, mai shelulit, so what is this שלולית shelulit which also
will help us explain this שלולית shelulit we mentioned before that exempts
you if the fire crosses it? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מקום
שמי גשמים שוללים שם, amar rav yehuda amar shmuel makom she-mei geshamim
sholelim sham, a place where like, you know, the rainwater like, you
know, just streams there. So it's
not actually like a—you know, I don't know if that's supposed to
indicate that it's some type of a of a small ditch that
you've dug in order to serve as like a drainpipe, you know,
that gets all the rainwater collects there and goes, or it's just
like a naturally low place, you know, it's always like when it
rains a lot there's always these places on the street where because
of the curvature, right, the water tends to like gather in a
particular place and go down there, right? So anyway, presumably if it's
something that—that divides the field for פאה, peah, it is some type
of a semi-permanent feature of the field. It's not just while the
rain is going there. So presumably it has worn out some type
of a crevice, you know, where the rain is passing through.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מקום שמי גשמים שוללים שם. amar rav
yehuda amar shmuel makom she-mei geshamim sholelim sham. רב ביבי אמר רבי
יוחנן אמת המים שמחלקת שלל לאגפיה, rav bibi amar rabbi yochanan amat
ha-mayim she-mechaleket shalal le-agafeha, no, it is some type of a— of
a
ditch of water that the word שלולית shululit is not to gather,
but שלל shallal is like the booty that it spreads out, you
know,
its booty to its banks, you know, so it gets filled with
water and then it overflows. Okay.
מאן דאמר Man de'amar מקום שהגשמים שופכים שם, makom shehageshamim shofchim sham,
if you say that there's a place where the water rainwater collects
there, כל שכן kol sheken אמת המים, amas hamayim, certainly this type
of an אמת המים amas hamayim which is like a dug, you
know, ditch. It's not just a natural thing that gets formed, that's
a much bigger type of a break in the field. But we're
talking about פאה. pe'ah. ומאן דאמר Uman de'amar אמת המים, amas hamayim,
but if it's only this ditch of water, אבל מקום שהגשמים שופכים
שם aval makom shehageshamim shofchim sham לא מחשקי, lo machshiki, that doesn't
separate the field. דהנו
בגני דארעא מיקרו, Dehanu bagnei de'ara mikru, those are just called like
puddles in the ground, right? If it's not like actually a man-made
thing and it's just a natural place where water collects, that's not
significant enough to divide up the field, therefore for פאה. pe'ah. But
we brought it in because we mentioned שלולית shululit is something for
a fire. Okay. So, what we have now is, what have we
said? That you make a fire in your field, if the fence
is if the wall is high enough or if it, you know,
has to pass, you know, this type of a large distance or
some type of a place of water, you're going to be exempt.
Of course the key question always is like, how do we measure,
you know, what size of the fire, what the nature of the
fire is when you're making it to determine, you know, what type
of how high the wall has to be and all these other
circumstances. Is it its potential, like what could be anticipated as its
potential, you know, all these sort of key questions are missing. Let's
look at the next משנה. mishna.
המדליק בתוך שלו. Hamadlik betoch shelo. Now, you lit a fire in
your field, presumably was the case in the previous משנה. mishna. עד
כמה תעבור הדליקה? Ad kama ta'avor hadleika? Now here presumably you don't
have a wall, you just have an open field but there's a
lot of flat land and distance. How far does it have to
spread before you're considered to be responsible? So, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer, רואין אותו כאילו הוא באמצע בית
כור. ro'in oto ke'ilu hu be'emtza beit kor. You look at the
person as if he's in the middle of a בית כור, beit
kor, which is I think
73 אמות amot by 73 אמות amot about a square area. So
that would mean if you're in the middle of it, it would
have to pass something like like a 32 אמות amot in order
and you know and only then would you be חייב. chayav. Is
that what it says there? Does it give you the dimensions there,
David? Let me check. I think it's like 73 and a half
אמות amot in each direction or something like that.
בית כור Beit kor
measures for 274 by 274.
Oh, 274 by 274 אמות.
amot. אמות, amot, yeah.
Oh, okay, so I was wrong.
The center is 137.
Oh, okay. I think I was doing I guess I was doing
a quarter of that. Okay, so anyway, fine. Okay, so I got
the numbers wrong. Okay, so 137 אמות, amot, and after that point
you'd be פטור. patur. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer ט"ז אמות
tet-zayin amot כדרך רשות הרבים. kederech reshut harabbim. And now we understand
why we quoted רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer before. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
said, no, once 16 after 16 אמות, amot, you know, then you're
פטור. patur. If there were 16 אמות amot for it to pass,
it's not expected that a normal fire will spread beyond that, so
anything more than that you would be exempt. Okay, now that explains
now why when it said before רשות הרבים reshut harabbim in the
previous משנה, mishna, we said that was רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, because
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is 16
אמות. amot. Okay, so our previous משנה, mishna, if you think about
it, like it's one thing to say a wall or river, right,
those things really do stop a fire, but just plain, you know,
straight horizontal distance, you know, you would think like really? 16 אמות?
amot? After 16 אמות amot you're no longer responsible? Like you much
more understand the earlier position that needs a hundred and something אמות.
amot. רבי עקיבא אומר חמשים אמה. Rabbi Akiva omer chamishim ama. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says 50 אמה, ama, like like 75 feet. Okay.
רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer שלם ישלם המבעיר את הבערה. shallem
yeshallem hamav'ir et hab'era. הכל לפי הדליקה. Hakol lefi hadleika. Thank you.
He says like, you guys which you know, it's all based on
the fire. Like what do you mean 50, 16? Like you got
to look, how big of a fire are you making? How much
fuel is there on your ground? What are the expected wind conditions?
Like you got I mean, that's the only thing that makes sense.
How do you give these arbitrary numbers? Now, part of the reason
that the rabbis might give those arbitrary numbers is that it's so
impossible, you know, practically to adjudicate a case. Like how are we
going to retroactively figure out exactly what the wind conditions were and
how much fuel you had and exactly how big the fire was,
like was people taking pictures at the time? I mean, you know,
right? So, but on the other hand, it's still so arbitrary, those
other numbers, right? So that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said. Okay,
so מר Mar says, but now the גמרא Gemara thinks that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying that basically saying הכל לפי הדליקה hakol
lefi hadleika means you're always going to pay. Like שלם ישלם. shallem
yeshallem. Which is an interesting point, you know, the fire is the
one thing in the פסוקים pesukim that it doesn't say that if
you watch it you're פטור. patur. Like it says by the שור
shor it says ולא ישמרנו, velo yishmerennu, right? בור Bor it says
ולא יכסנו. velo yechassennu. And by the fire it says... כי תצא
אש, ki tetzei esh, the fire goes out, שלם ישלם. shalaim yeshalem.
It never says you're פטור, patur, which you can understand, right? Because
a fire like it always has this tremendous potential that maybe can't
be—I mean you could still say I've done everything normal and the
everything—and
it was complete אונס, ones, completely unexpected. But
anyway—well, right. I mean, you could have taken—right, you could have taken
like precautions in terms of the wall you made around the fire
and other types of things. But right, there's no like one—but
exactly—of the fire out of control, it like just
took—right, and once it's out of control, then it—then it's over. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara initially seems that רב שמעון Rebbe Shimon just
means, no, you always pay. So the גמרא Gemara says, וסבר רב
שמעון שיעור בדליקה? v'savar Rebbe Shimon shiur badleika? Does רב שמעון Rebbe
Shimon not hold that there's an amount of guarding that you can
do for a fire and be exempt? והתנן, v'hatnan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, לא יעמיד אדם תנור בתוך הבית אלא אם כן
יש על גביו גבוה ארבע אמות. lo ya'amid adam tanur betoch habayit
ela im kein yesh al gabav gavo'ah arba amot. Now, this is
an interesting הלכה. halacha. בבא קמא Bava Kamma talks about after the
fact. You caused damage, how much do you have to pay? בבא
בתרא Bava Batra talks about before the fact. בבא בתרא Bava Batra
is laws of neighbors. And I basically have a right, like someone
was asking me the other day, does fire damage include when you
have to pay for fire does it include smoke damage? Which I
think is a great question. And I'll have to find the answer.
But in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, the question is not if we're
neighbors, not if like under what circumstances do you pay me, but
under what circumstances can I tell you, you've got that oven, it's
creating an enormous amount of smoke which is polluting my property. You
have to move it further away from the property line. You have
to do something. You have this beehive, those bees are coming into
my property. So that's like the laws of neighbors which create what's
called הרחקת נזיקין. harchakat nezikin. What I can demand of you to
keep your stuff away to prevent me from being damaged, which is
not the question of compensation after the fact. So that's the case
here. I've got an oven in a house and you're living either
on the top floor or the bottom floor and I've got my
oven and I can't tell you, oh, I'm doing with my oven,
it's none of your business. No, you can say, look, that oven
is a fire hazard and you are not allowed to have that
oven in your part of the house without actually making certain precautions.
רש"י Rashi actually says it's not just the person at the bottom
or the top of the house, it's like the people of the
city. It's actually like a city imposing, like what do they call,
like not a—as a fire code. People of the city imposing like
these safety laws. You being responsible with your oven is all of
our business and we can tell you this is what you have
to do. Okay. So here's what it says. לא יעמיד אדם תנור
בתוך הבית, lo ya'amid adam tanur betoch habayit, you can't have an
oven in your house, אלא אם
כן יש על גביו גבוה ארבע אמות. ela im kein yesh al
gabav gavo'ah arba amot. There has to be four אמות amot between
the top of the oven and the roof, okay, otherwise obviously it's
a fire hazard. היה מעמידו בעליה, hayah ma'amido b'aliyah, if it was
in the second story, עד שיהא תחתיו מעזיבה שלשה טפחים. ad sheyehai
tachtav ma'aziva shlosha tfachim. In addition to the distance between the top
and the roof, there also has to be the floor has to
be like three טפחים tfachim thick so it doesn't obviously the heat
of it doesn't break through the floor. ובכירה, u'v'kira, which is a
type of an oven which is—has less concentrated heat, טפח, tefach, it
only needs a טפח. tefach. אם הזיק משלם מה שהזיק, im hizik
mshalem mah shehizik,
and even if you've taken these precautions, the משנה Mishnah here is
saying, if it actually—fire does start, you're liable. רב שמעון אומר, Rebbe
Shimon omer, right, because there's a different הלכה halacha between
what we can demand of you to prevent us from being hurt
and then the question
of what liability you have if something happens. רב שמעון אומר, Rebbe
Shimon omer, רב שמעון Rebbe Shimon says, לא נאמרו שיעורים הללו, lo
ne'emru shiurim halalu, only the whole reason for these things, for
these particular amounts of distance that you have to do,
אלא שאם הזיק פטור מלשלם. ela she'im hizik patur milshalem. It's to
tell you, meaning, if you've taken those precautions, then it means if
something happens you're exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says, you see that
רב שמעון Rebbe Shimon says you can do things to be protective
of a fire in order to be exempt. Or how come in
our משנה Mishnah it sounds like he's saying there's nothing you can
do? Of course, one might imagine that the difference between a contained
fire or an exposed fire, different types of things, but it's presumably
nobody disagrees, says the משנה, Mishnah, that you can take precautions and
be פטור. patur. So what does רב שמעון Rebbe Shimon mean? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה,
amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha, הכל לפי גובה הדליקה. hakol lefi govah hadleika.
He doesn't mean you always pay. He means that it's also based
on the particulars, based on how big the fire is would determine
and I would also say based on what kindling there is on
the ground would determine how much of a distance you need in
order to be exempt, in order to say that you've made clear
it won't go out of your property. אמר רב יוסף אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון. amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbe Shimon. We rule like רב שמעון. Rebbe Shimon.
וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון, v'chein amar Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbe Shimon, which is like relieving because some
of these numbers before, right, the four אמות, amot, this, that, and
the straight, the bent,
it's like you need—like you feel that on the one hand while
there's two problems. On the one hand you feel the numbers are
arbitrary. You agree with רב שמעון Rebbe Shimon that you need to
assess each case based on its circumstances. But the other sort of,
I guess, frustrate— rating thing was the question about like how do
you determine it? Like if I've got a flame that's only this
big, right, do you say like okay, then this amount of distance,
you say wait wait wait, based on prevailing wind conditions there's this
likelihood that it would get to be a bigger flame and then
you're going to need a higher fence or more distance. Like how
much do you factor in? Do you assess it based on the
current reality or based on the possible future way in which the
fire could grow? You know, so I don't really know the answer.
I mean logically you would think that any anything about determining if
whether it's protective is anticipating those possible future things. I mean if
you just think about the well, remember by the well we said
if you've got a cover that can protect it against oxes but
not camels, but camels are likely to be in the neighborhood, then
it's not a good cover. Right? So if you've got a fire
that could protect it based on this size but can't protect it
based on the size that it's likely to grow to based on
potential wind conditions and other types of things, so you really do
understand this idea like you know, the same way we never say
how thick does the cover of the well have to be, right?
What do you mean how thick? It depends on the circumstances. Everything
depends on the specific. Okay? So but how you exactly assess what
those specifics are I don't know, but at least you understand the
position. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. המדליק
את הגדיש, Hamadlik et hagedish,
now we finally return after we move beyond the question about שמירה,
shmira, we finally we go to this question. It's so interesting, I
don't can't explain the reverse order, but like all the other נזיקין
nezikin we first explain what the liability was and then we said
what the level of שמירה shmira was you needed. Here we sort
of start by the reverse, you know, what type of a שמירה
shmira is sufficient and then about what happens if you what is
the liability. And we finally turn to this issue of things buried
in the you know in the haystack, the needle in the- anyway,
you know, the debate of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the חכמים Chachamim
about טמון, tamun, about buried things. So let's take a look. המדליק
את הגדיש, Hamadlik et hagedish, you lit a stack of grain.
והיו בו כלים, v'hayu vo kelim, and there were vessels in it.
Okay? ודלקו, v'dalku, and they and they lit on fire and they
burnt. רבי יהודה אומר משלם מה שבתוכו, Rebbi Yehuda omer meshalem ma
shebetokho, he has to pay even if something is buried in the
haystack. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say אינו משלם אלא
גדיש חטים או של שעורים, eino meshalem ela gedish chitim o shel
seorim, no, you look at it as if what you would have
expected to be in it. If all you saw on the outside
was a big stack of a wheat, then you pay as if
there was it was all wheat, or if it was all barley.
You don't pay if there was something buried hidden in it that
was like not normal thing.
Okay? Now we're going to get back to this issue about things
hidden in the, you know, buried things for fire, but we're going
to first for a minute speak about this other part of this
משנה Mishnah which we've seen multiple times. היה גדי כפות לו, haya
gedi kafut lo, let's say there was a a goat that was
bound up near this stack of of wheat. ועבד סמוך לו, v'eved
samukh lo, and a slave that was nearby. ונשרף עמו, v'nisraf imo,
חייב. chayav. You're חייב. chayav. Why you're חייב? chayav? Because even if
the slave died, you're not going to say קים ליה בדרבה מיניה
kim leih bid'raba minei because, you know, what you normally say in
a case of something that caused death, because he could have run
away. He wasn't, the slave wasn't bound. The reason that you're חייב
chayav for the- if the גדי gedi wasn't bound you'd also be
פטור patur because the גדי gedi should have run away, and that's
not- assuming that the that there was some ability to run away,
it wasn't trapped. Okay? So you're only חייב chayav if both things
are true: the גדי gedi was bound, so you- he couldn't have
run away, and the עבד eved was unbound so you can't say
קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kim leih bid'raba minei. All right, so in
that case you're going to be חייב. chayav. However, עבד כפות לו,
eved kafut lo, if the עבד eved was bound and therefore he
was definitely he couldn't have run away, so basically what happened was
an act of murder, so you're going to say קים ליה, kim
leih, so you'll be פטור patur on everything. Or, the ו vav
here is read as an or, or גדי סמוך לו, gedi samukh
lo, or if the goat was unbound, so then you're not liable
for that
because it should have run away. In that case, ונשרף עמו פטור,
v'nisraf imo patur, you're פטור, patur, you're exempt. Okay, so that was
that case we've had that before about the goat and the slave
and about whether fire is like חציו chitzov and therefore would you
say a principle of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim leih bid'raba minei,
it's like an act of murder. Now back to the issue of
טמון. tamun. ומודים חכמים
לרבי יהודה, umodim chachamim l'Rebbi Yehuda, the חכמים Chachamim agree with רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda and the חכמים Chachamim say that you are not
liable for something that is buried in the haystack במדליק את הבירה,
b'madlik et habirah, if you lit a like a castle, like a
big a house, שהוא משלם כל מה שבתוכו, shehu meshalem kol ma
shebetokho, you pay for all the furniture, everything that's in it, שכן
דרך בני אדם להניח בבתים, sheken derekh bnei adam lehaniach b'vatim, because
it's people normally keep things in their house, of course you're going
to be liable. Now, the simple sense of this if we had
not been trained since the beginning of the מסכת Masechet to say
that the חכמים Chachamim have this arbitrary exemption of טמון, tamun, of
things that are buried, we would have said that nobody here has
some special הלכה halacha that there's some exemption for something that's buried.
The חכמים Chachamim are just saying you're not liable for something that
nobody reasonably could have expected. You happen to have, you know, your
your Van Gogh painting buried in your haystack, you can't make me-
pay for that, right? There's also a whole question about proving it.
I guess you could prove it, you go afterwards and see the
chars or something. But nevertheless, like, that seems to be אף af
something I should have expected, you know, you keep stuff in your
house, and your house burned down, and I was making a fire
that could have burned down your house. Of course I should pay
for things that are in it. But if I was making a
fire in the middle of a field and all I saw around
me was wheat, right? And all of a sudden you find out
that you buried something precious in that wheat, like, that's not my
responsibility. Yes?
But I understand it's my wheat you buried your Van Gogh in.
Well if it's
your wheat, I mean,
you're entitled to do what right.
Right. You can do whatever you want.
Right. And if my ox goes ahead and, you know, and gores,
whatever, like, you know, gores, like, like
knocks down a wall, let's say, you know, like it's a מזיק,
mazik, it hits down a wall or whatever, and buried and you
were and you had some something hidden in that wall, right, so
I'd be חייב, chayav, right? So why is it different by the
fire? So it might be though here the thing is, is and
this might be the אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, I guess. Normally we
assume if אש משום חציו esh mishum chitzav that it's more of
a liability. But if you think about it in terms of, like,
what would be considered as if I did that act, like, so
maybe if like I'm making a fire and I should expect, I
I'm negligent and I should have been aware that it could have
escaped and done all these things, it's like I destroyed them. But
something that I had no reason to expect, like, you can't really
attribute it so much as if I did it. Meaning, the אש
משום חציו esh mishum chitzav makes me more to blame, but also
makes it harder to say I did a particular thing. Right? When
as you if you say that it's because the animal did the
act, well my animal destroyed this hidden this thing that was hidden
in the wall, right? That it did. I have to pay for
it. It's my animal, I'm responsible. My אש esh did destroy something,
so if you sort of like אש משום ממונו, esh mishum mamono,
you would have said my fire burned something, I have to pay
for it. But if you have to say it was like I
destroyed it, right, so then if I weren't if I didn't have
a reason to expect it, that wasn't my sort of incorp- like
part of my initial negligence. So I agree, it's strange, right? Why
here all of a sudden, you know, do we- does it matter
if I could have expected or not? It might make a little
more sense as I said, if it has to be as if
I did it, right, as opposed to other things when my animal,
when my ox does it, then I pay for whatever my ox
does. But here to make it like as if I did it,
maybe you could say if I wasn't aware. Okay, but that's I
would say however you explain it, certainly I would say the simple
sense of the משנה mishna is that is that there's no arbitrary
הלכה halacha of something being hidden. It's the question that since I
didn't have a reason to expect it, I'm exempt. The גמרא, gemara,
until now we were used to the idea that there is this
arbitrary הלכה, halacha, and the גמרא gemara is going to go back
and make make it that there is going to be this arbitrary
הלכה. halacha. You wanted to say something else? Is this all assuming
accidental or like if I go and purposely set your haystack on
fire? No, well that's what we'll see about that, something very similar
to that in the גמרא. gemara. So the גמרא gemara is going
to make that distinction. The other thing I should say about the
funny thing about the house is there seems to me to be
a difference between a house and a place where I expect people
to hide things. Like let's say a wall is a place where
people hide things, like the גמרא gemara talks about, you know, you
have these little holes in the wall, and people hide things. So
there it's a place you could say okay, it's buried, but I
should have expected that people hide things. But in a house, I
wouldn't say stuff in a house is buried. Like, you walk into
a house, you can see it. You have to be allowed entry
into the house, but it's not exactly out in the open, but
it's not exactly the same as being buried, you know? Right? So
it's also a difference.
Let's take a look at what the גמרא gemara says. Okay. אמר
רב כהנא amar Rav Kahana says רב כהנא. Rav Kahana.
מחלוקת במדליק בתוך שלו והלכה והלכה בתוך של חבירו.
machlokes
bemadlik
betoch shelo vehalcha vehalcha betoch shel chaveiro. This debate of טמון tamun
is only when it was a fire in your domain and it
spread. רבי יהודה מחייב בנזקי טמון באש, Rebbi Yehuda mechayev benizkei tamun
ba-esh, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you're חייב. chayav. רבנן פטרי, Rabanan
patri, and the רבנן Rabanan exempt. Right? Remember when it starts in
your domain and it spreads, it's a little bit more like אש
משום ממונו. esh mishum mamono. It's less sort of seen as like
you are, you know, willfully doing it. אבל במדליק בתוך של חבירו,
aval bemadlik betoch shel chaveiro, this is very much then along the
lines you said. If you started by putting a fire in your
friend's property, דכולי עלמא משלם כל מה שבתוכה, dekuli alma meshalem kol
mah shebetocha, then you don't get any exemptions. Then it's like, you
know, you start by this act of violation, you're responsible for anything
that comes out of it. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, says
רבא, Rava, אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's true, אדקתני סיפא, adkatani
seifa, the end of the משנה mishna says מודים חכמים לרבי יהודה
במדליק את הבירה שמשלם כל מה שבתוכה, modim chachamim leRebbi Yehuda bemadlik
es habirah shemeshalem kol mah shebetocha, רבנן Rabanan agree when you light
a house you pay everything that's in it. שכן דרך בני אדם
להניח בבתים, sheken derech benei adam lehaniach bevattim, people leave things in
their houses. לפלוג ולתני בדידה, liplog velisni bedidih, why not make a
distinction within the very case of the haystack? במה דברים אמורים במדליק
בתוך שלו, bameh devarim amurim bemadlik betoch shelo, when are you exempt?
When you started in your property and it spread, והלכה והלכה בתוך
של חבירו, vehalcha vehalcha betoch shel chaveiro, and then it went into
the friend's property. אבל מדליק בתוך של חבירו, aval madlik betoch shel
chaveiro, if you started in your friend's property, דכולי עלמא משלם כל
מה שהיה בתוכה, dekuli alma meshalem kol mah shehayah betocha, you pay
everything. And the way תוספות Tosafot also says it, the phrase מדליק
את הבירה, madlik es habirah, lighting a house, sounds like you lit
your friend's property. You went into your friend's property and you torched
his house. So it shouldn't have anything to do with the fact
that people normally leave things in their houses, it should just have
to do with the fact that you're always liable according to this
idea. אלא אמר רבא בתרתי פליגי. Ella amar Rava bitartei pligi. So
רבא Rava says there are two degrees of the debate and this
sort of salvages the idea of the משנה Mishnah that what you
could expect and also the idea of there being an arbitrary exemption.
Okay, so פליגי במדליק בתוך שלו והלכה ואכלה בתוך של חבירו. Pligi
b'madlik b'toch shelo v'halcha v'achla b'toch shel chaveiro. This is a debate
when it starts in your property and it spreads. רבי יהודה מחייב
את הטמון באש ורבנן סברי לא מחייב. Rabbi Yehuda mechayev es hatamun
ba'eish v'rabanan savri lo mechayev. There, it's an arbitrary exemption when it
spreads and it's not in and then whether it's something that could
be expected or couldn't be expected, according to the rabbis you're always
exempt if it was buried, which is like a really disturbing idea,
especially if you consider things in a house to be buried. So
I'm irresponsible, a fire in my property and it spreads and it
burns down your house. I only have to pay for the house,
I don't have to pay for any of the any of the
contents of the house, right? Even because that's what it says, when
it starts in your property, that's an arbitrary exemption according to the
חכמים. Chachamim. רבנן סברי לא מחייב. Rabanan savri lo mechayev. ופליגי נמי
במדליק בתוך של חבירו. U'pligi nami b'madlik b'toch shel chaveiro. And then
they also debate when it's in your when you start in the
friend's property. רבי יהודה סבר משלם כל מה שבתוכו, Rabbi Yehuda savar
meshaleim kol mah she'be'tocho, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of course continues of
course to say you always pay, ואפילו ארנקי, v'afilu arneki, even if
it would be like a wallet. ורבנן סברי לא. v'rabanan savri lo.
כלים שדרכן להטמין בגדיש, Keilim she'darkan lehatmin b'gadish, כגון מורגי וכלי בקר,
k'gon murgi u'chli bakar, things that are normally hidden, let's say you
lit not a house, but you know, you lit a stack of
grain. So things that people normally bury in a stack of grain,
like these various types of, you know, things that they would use,
the beams that they would use, the ידוכתא yeduchta or whatever that
they would use on their animals. So those things, הוה משלם, hu
meshaleim, that you pay, because that could have been expected. כלים שאין
דרכן להטמין בגדיש, Keilim she'ein darkan lehatmin b'gadish, things that you don't
normally bury, לא משלם, lo meshaleim, you would not pay. So therefore,
when the rabbis say when you light your friend's house you pay
because people normally hide things there, that's because you started in your
friend's property. When you start in your property, you're always exempt. Okay,
arbitrary exemption. When you start in your friend's property, then you would
be liable for anything that normally should be expected. Now, again, again,
I don't know if that is, you know, how much is that
different than starting in your friend's property but trying to destroy or
just, you know, I mean, there's ways I could start in my
friend's property, right? It's like, you know, I've, I don't know, I
was camping out in your in your backyard without your permission, in
your forest, and I was making a little fire, you know, and
cooking something. And then there's I take a torch and I'm trying
to torch your property, right? There's big differences of starting in your
friend's property, right? Which is also, by the way, the question I've
always asked about אש משום חציו ומשום ממונו. eish mishum chitzav u'mishum
mamono. Like let's say I literally take a torch and, you know,
light your haystack and burn it down. Is that אש eish or
do would everybody say that's אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, you know? So
anyway, one wonders, right, would there be a case where it's like
בכוונה b'chavanah where even if it's not דרכו darko you'd be חייב
chayav because then it would much more be אדם המזיק, adam hamazik,
that's not stated in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. What is the reason
the word hidden in terms of a house, since that is the
natural... That's what I said. That whole calling it buried, it's really
not buried, it's just like not exposed, which is really the phrase
the גמרא Gemara used before, מה קמה בגלוי, mah kamah b'galui, like
standing grain is exposed. So somehow something not exposed, right? I, you
know, I don't really get it. Somehow it seems to be this
idea that it has to be exposed. Somehow seems to be like,
I light a fire and like, you know, you sort of like
you look around and sort of the things that are like there
that are visible are like the potential, you know, sort of fuel
of the fire. So and other things are like I I don't
really get it, but there's some idea about that that there's just
this exemption if it's not exposed. Okay, but that's when you start
by your own. When you start somebody else's, fundamentally much more of
a violation or of an אדם המזיק adam hamazik component and then
but you still have this distinction of could you expect it or
not expect it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught, המדליק את הגדיש והיו בו כלים
דדלקו, hamadlik es hagadish v'hayu vo keilim d'dalku, you lit this stack
of grain and there were some vessels in it and they burned.
רבי יהודה אומר משלם כל מה שהיה בתוכו, Rabbi Yehuda omer meshaleim
kol mah she'hayah b'tocho, you pay everything, וחכמים אומרים אינו משלם אלא
גדיש של חטים או גדיש של שעורים, v'chachamim omrim eino meshaleim ella
gadish shel chitim o gadish shel se'orim, you only pay as if
it were a whole stack of wheat or of barley. רואים מקום
כלים כאילו הוא מלא תבואה, Ro'im mekom keilim k'ilu hu malei tvuah,
but you pay at least as what you should have expected to
be there. You don't pay for the כלים, keilim, but you don't
totally exempt, you look at it as if it's filled with grain.
Now again, the funny thing is here the language sounds like you
went into your friend's property and you lit his stack of grain.
But based on what we just said, if that were true, you
would pay for the כלים, keilim, especially כלים keilim that normally would
be there. Okay, so we have to assume that the scenario here
is that you lit in your property and it spread, which is
actually what the next line of the ברייתא Baraisa says. במה דברים
אמורים במדליק בתוך שלו, Bameh devarim amurim b'madlik b'toch shelo, when you
lit in your property, והלכה ודלקה בתוך של חבירו, v'halcha v'dalka b'toch
shel chaveiro, in that case, that's when you're going to be פטור,
pattur, because that's what we said is טמון באש. tamun ba'eish. That's
the arbitrary exemption when it spread from your property out. אבל מדליק
בתוך של חבירו, Aval madlik b'toch shel chaveiro, but if you started
in your friend's property... משלם כל מה שהיה בתוכו, meshalem kol mah
shehayah betocho, you pay everything. Now, of course this is somewhat consistent
with what we said before, the difference between starting in yours starting
in the friend's, but what it should have said here is if
it was something that could have been expected. But since that's the
scenario, the scenario is that there were כלים keilim in a haystack,
which presumably means the normal types of כלים keilim that there would
be in a haystack, okay? So therefore you're going to pay. So
this ברייתא Beraita supports what רבא Rava was saying. If you start
in your property and it spreads, it's an arbitrary exemption. If you
start in your friend's property, you're going to be חייב chayav at
least for the things that could have been expected to have been
there. All right, so is that clear? So basically, although a little
vague, we've restated what we said until now. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ומודה רבי יהודה. U-modeh Rabbi Yehuda. Now רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you're always חייב. chayav. He agrees לחכמים la-Chachamim במשרה
מקום לחברו להגדיש גדיש, bi-mashreh makom le-chaveiro le-hagdish gadish, that he used
basically, you know, I grant David and I let you sure you
want to use my property? Come in and you know make some
stack your grain, be my friend, be my guest. והגדיש והטמין, V'higdish
v'hitmin, and you went and you stacked your grain and you buried
something in your grain, שאינו משלם אלא דמי גדיש בלבד. she-eino meshalem
ela dmei gadish bilvad. Then I only have to pay for it
because then I could presumably say, now you remember a while ago
we talked about if I give you permission to come into my
property and I have more liability, I'm like explicitly accepting responsibility for
stuff you're bringing in. But here, on the other hand, I can
say to you, I only gave you permission for your grain. I
didn't tell you you could hide your vessels. So the fact I
don't have a right to tell you what you can do on
your property, right? So if my thing burnt down your thing on
your property, what do you mean, oh I didn't expect it, it's
my property I can do what I want. But here I could
say I had a right to assume that the only thing that
was there was grain because that's the only thing I allowed you
to put there. All right, so in that case I would not
have to pay for other things that you hid. Now, if I
gave you permission, you know, let's stop here because the next line
is very—no let's read it. It's confusing but we might as well
be done with it now and then we'll continue something else tomorrow.
להגדיש חטים והגדיש שעורים. Le-hagdish chittim v'higdish seorim. I gave you the
permission to put wheat and you put barley. So in that case
I'm obviously going to pay only for the barley because it only
destroyed barley. That's the easy case. שעורים והגדיש חטים. Seorim v'higdish chittim.
If I gave you permission for barley and you put wheat, okay,
so all these things we're going to say I only pay for
barley. Now that's interesting. I gave you permission to put barley, you
used it to put wheat, it burnt it down, so that would
be sort of like, you know, that's sort of like a—like when
you come into my property without permission and my ox gores you,
I'm פטור. patur. So you brought your wheat into your property without
my permission, I only gave you permission for barley, so if it
burns down the wheat, I'm פטור. patur. I'm responsible as if it
were barley, but I'm going to be פטור patur for the fact
that it was wheat—you didn't have permission to have wheat here. Now
how about it's חטים וחיפון בשעורים? chittim v'chipun be-seorim? It's wheat that
you covered with barley. Well, if it was all wheat I'm going
to be פטור patur from—from paying wheat because you didn't have the
right. So this as well. Wheat that looks like barley, but also
I'm going to be פטור patur for the wheat part of it
because you didn't have a right to have wheat here. How about
שעורים וחיפון בחטים? seorim v'chipun be-chittim? How about you brought in barley
and you covered them with wheat? Well, at the end of the
day, in all these cases you only had right to barley here.
So in all these cases שאינו משלם אלא דמי שעורים בלבד. she-eino
meshalem ela dmei seorim bilvad. Okay, so even though those, you know,
in a way those could be a case of טמון tamun if
you did it in your property, you know, you had wheat covered
with barley, barley covered with wheat, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say
you pay what was really there. But if I only gave you
permission to do barley, then anything you got going on in this
field that's more than barley is something that you're in my field
without permission and I'm going to be פטור patur for. Vice versa,
if I give you permission for wheat—that's interesting, if I gave permission
for wheat and you brought in barley, but barley costs less than
wheat, what are you saying? That since fundamentally you're without permission... Yeah,
you see that's an interesting thing. We don't say for example when
I gave your permission for wheat and you bring—for barley and you
bring in wheat that I'm totally פטור. patur. Like somehow I'm still
liable for the cost of the barley, so because—yeah, it's a funny
idea. You're right. It's not like oh, you had no permission for
this object I have no liability. Like since you—right—now since you could
have brought in barley, at least I have to pay you as
if it were barley. Sort of like the כלים, keilim, like because—I
don't have to pay you for the כלים keilim but I have
to pay you as if they were the thing they should have
been there. It's a funny idea, yeah. Also one might be more
flammable than the other. Ah, that's a
good point too. All right, we're done.